Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Alright, so today's דף daf is דף
י. Daf Yud. And we pick up at the bottom of טו
עמוד ב, tet vav amud bet, the two dots, four lines from
the bottom, תנו רבנן. tanoo rabanan. So we are up to the
issue here about ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, about the first of תשרי
Tishrei being the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for planting, for נטיעה. netia.
Which means, as opposed to what we've said and what we'll come
back to, which is that ראש השנה... Rosh Hashanah... the first of
תשרי Tishrei is the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for
other
agricultural issues like שמיטה shmita and יובל, yovel, which basically means that
the new year within the שמיטה shmita cycle or the beginning of
the יובל yovel year begins on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in terms
of the calendar year and how you identify what calendar year it
is. This has to do more with the counting of age, in
a way maybe think of it similar to the issue of the
kings, where it's for a particular planting that you do, you planted
a new tree, how many years old is the tree? So not
like is it the third year of the cycle of the שמיטה
shmita or the seventh year of the cycle of the יובל yovel
cycle, which is like for everybody what year it is, but it's
for the particular thing that I did, when do we sort of
increment its age? So you plant a new tree and you have
to wait for it to be after its own first three years
of its planting, it's ערלה orlah and only then... then you don't
eat the fruit right away anyway, then it's רבעי, reva'i, fourth year
fruit, which you redeem and you eat and you use the money
in ירושלים Yerushalayim or you bring the fruit and you eat it
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and the fifth year you can eat it straight
without any restrictions. So you would have naturally thought it means three
years from you know, from its birthday, you know, or like from
day to day, you know, from the same day of the year
to the same day in the next year. But the משנה Mishna
teaches that no, it's on תשרי Tishrei that's when it becomes enters
into its second year. So you could have planted it a month,
we'll see, maybe maybe even less, but let's say a month before
תשרי Tishrei and then you could have planted it on ראש חודש
אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul and then come תשרי Tishrei it's already second
year. Okay? So it'll be done with its three years after two
years and a month, not even after three years.
And you eat the fruit from the first year? What?
Can you sell the fruit from the first year? No, ערלה orlah
is even forbidden in benefit, you can't do anything with it. Now
normally most trees don't produce fruit in their first three years, but
the bigger challenge is that when it's not a new planting but
when it's like a graft, a graft, הברכה, hovrakha, right. So we'll
talk about that. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
תנו רבנן, Tanoo rabanan, our Rabbis taught: אחד הנוטע, echad hanotea, and
this is what we start with, whether you plant; ואחד המבריך, ve'echad
hamavrich, or whether you do מבריך, mavrich, which is basically you take...
where are my markers? Do I not have any markers?
Okay, we don't have any markers. Alright, so מבריך mavrich is when
you basically take a take a branch and you bend it underground
and it comes out...
oh there's a good picture inside, okay, very good.
Alright, that's an illustration, I would call it not a picture, but
okay. You take a plant and you sort of bend it underground
and then it starts and then you help it come up straight
here, you support it up and then it sort of comes out
as another tree. Okay?
So what does that do?
It creates another tree. Like why you do that rather than cutting
it and replanting? Maybe because it's still getting the nutrients from the
old tree. I'm I'm sure they know what they're talking you know,
what they're talking about. This is all over פאה. Pe'ah. Right, מבריכה.
mavri'ah.
Okay. ואחד המרכיב, ve'echad hamarkiv, or whether you do מרכיב, markiv, that's
grafting. Okay, so these are all ways in which it's considered a
new planting.
ערב שביעית Erev Shvi'it שלושים יום לפני ראש השנה, shloshim yom lifnei
Rosh Hashanah, so if you did this 30 days before שמיטה shmita
begins, before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah of שמיטה, shmita, so basically like
ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul or earlier... oh so lo or
no... before ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, excuse me,
then עלתה לו שנה, altah lo shana, then it counts as the
year, meaning for ערלה orlah purposes, when it comes ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, since it was planted 30 days before, it's now considered to
be in year two from the ערלה orlah counting. ומותר לקיימן בשביעית,
umutur lekayman baShvi'it,
and you could allow it to continue to grow on שביעית. Shvi'it.
פחות משלושים יום לפני ראש השנה, Pachot mishloshim yom lifnei Rosh Hashanah,
if it is on ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul or later
because אלול Elul has 29 days, then לא עלתה לו שנה, lo
altah lo shana, it does not count as a year, so come
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah it is still year one of its being
a tree, thank you, not year two. ואסור לקיימן בשביעית, ve'asur lekayman
baShvi'it,
and you cannot keep it in שמיטה shmita now. What is this
idea of 30 days? We will see in a minute. There are
actually a difference between these 30 days and the גמרא's Gemara going
to sort of conflate them or, dare I say, graft them. The
גמרא Gemara
anyway... there's actually a slight difference. The idea before ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah
of שמיטה shmita is that... well for now, we'll modify it in
a minute, but is for now let's assume it's this idea of
תוספת, tosefet, right? We learned before that you have to be מוסיף
mosif on שמיטה, shmita, you have to start prohibitions before. We're going
to find out that if you planted a tree on שמיטה, shmita,
let's say on שמיטה shmita itself, you would have to pull it
out of the ground. or ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is of שמיטה
Shmita is that, well for now we'll modify it in a minute,
but is for now let's assume it's this idea of תוספת. Tosefet.
Right? We learned before that you have to be מוסיף mosif on
שמיטה, Shmita, you have to start the prohibition before. We're going to
find out that if you planted a tree on שמיטה, Shmita, let's
say on שמיטה Shmita itself, you would have to pull it out
of the ground. You couldn't let it stay. So if you plant
a tree before שמיטה Shmita during the תוספת Tosefet period, you also
would have to uproot it. So one thing this is teaching you,
we're going to modify it in a little bit, but for now
let's assume this is what it's saying, is that the תוספת Tosefet
period begins 30 days before. Okay, that's for הלכה Halacha of תוספת
שמיטה. Tosefet Shmita. What it's also telling you is for the ערלה
Orla period, 30 days, you need 30 days to have all of
the previous year so when comes ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah you can
say now is in year two. Anything less than that is it
barely got started so you can't already consider it to be year
two. You might remember that by the king, even if the king
was elected a day before
ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan or presumably ראש חודש תשרי Rosh
Chodesh Tishrei would come ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh of ניסן Nissan or
תשרי Tishrei depending on Jewish or not Jewish and then it would
be year two. Here we say you need 30 days so that
when it hits ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah it's counted as your two.
That presumably is not related to the שמיטה Shmita issue, it's a
question of how much do you need for תוספת. Tosefet. I mean
probably there's some relationship but it's not the exact same ruling. Okay,
so let's take a look then what the גמרא Gemara does with
this. By the way, I should say something about this מרכיב Markiv
where תוספות Tosfos has a discussion that in other sources it says
that when you do מרכיב, Markiv, when you do this bending and
regrowing, it's not considered a new planting and you do not apply
ערלה. Orla. And he says if you look at the four lines
before the lines get wide in תוספות, Tosfos, he says ויש לומר
דהתם כשלא נתקה מאביה ובאילן זקן והכא כשנתקה מאביה. V'yesh lomar de'hasam
keshelo nitteka mei'aviha, u'v'ilan zaken. V'hacha keshenitteka mei'aviha. So he says
that if you actually never cut it from the original tree and
even though it's growing out of a new place in the ground
it really is still physically an extension of the first tree. Like
it's a branch, it's a branch growing in a very bizarre way
and then it is not a new planting. But if you—so when
we're talking about being מרכיב Markiv being a new planting it's when
you do all of this and at some point you actually then
cut it and sever the connection. Okay, so now let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Rabbi Lookstein, I'm sorry, I don't understand the language of אסור לקיימן
בשביעית. assur l'kayman bashvi'is.
Just what I just said. If you plant something on שמיטה, Shmita,
it would have to be uprooted. Uprooted, so
מוסר אסור לקיימן mussar assur l'kayman is you cannot leave it the
way it is, you'd have to uproot it.
So this is within 30 days as if you planted
it on שמיטה Shmita because of תוספת. Tosefet. Okay, again, we'll modify
that in a minute, but that's the assumption now. Okay, anyway, on
top of יא עמוד א, Yud-Alef Amud-Alef,
and here's a very funny הלכה Halacha and I have to tell
you that I just got a שאלה Shayla about this literally like
two three weeks ago because ערלה Orla is applied not only in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael but even in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
So ערלה Orla and כלאים, Kilayim, although they're both agricultural,
apply also in—interestingly about the aspect of נטע רבעי. Neta Revai. You
might have ערלה Orla applying in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz but not
נטע רבעי. Neta Revai. Anyway, these can actually be הלכה למעשה. Halacha
L'maaseh. So let's take a look, especially now with people doing Jewish
farming and so on. So you would think, okay, it hits תשרי,
Tishrei, ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, now you're in year two. But there's—you
sort of pay back for it a little bit at the back
end because ופירות נטיעה זו אסורין, U'peiros netia zo asurim, the fruit
of this planting are forbidden, עד ט"ו בשבט, ad Tu B'Shvat, until
ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shvat again something like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. אם
לערלה ערלה, אם לרבעי רבעי. Im l'Orla Orla, im l'Revai Revai. If
it's for the third year then the third year of ערלה Orla
applies till ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shvat and if it's נטע רבעי Neta
Revai that applies to the fourth year. This is really a bad
time not to have markers. Let me go see if I can
find markers, I know it's Sunday and...
I guess
I
was thinking the same thing...
Normally I would have them in my backpack but I'm not going
to work.
This is so harsh.
Harsh, harsh judge... high expectations all the time...
What did I miss about Sunday?
What did I miss?
All right,
anyway.
So here you have as it's year one. I know I wish
we could do it right to left. All right, anyway we'll do
it from left to right. Okay so year one, okay, and here
is ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay so
whatever you planted it here.
Now whatever you planted the tree here. Dot dot dot dot dot
dot dot comes ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah you're in year two. Okay,
there's a whole other year, ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, now you're in
year three. Okay dot dot dot dot goes ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
so you would think now, right, this is year two now you're
in year three, you would think you go here now you're in
the clear, right? But no because the הלכה Halacha is
that ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shvat is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for trees.
At this stage before it's three years it's called נטיעה. netia. Remember
the לשון lashon is that תשרי Tishrei is ראש השנה לנטיעות. Rosh
Hashanah l'netios. But once it's three years old it's an אילן ilan
and for an אילן ilan the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for it
is ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shvat. So very bizarre הלכה Halacha here, at
some level it's already an אילן ilan but it's not yet its
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. It's like caught in between those two. It's
not yet—if it's not yet ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah why is it
an אילן? ilan? But anyway, somehow after three years it's no longer
a נטיעה netia but because it's an אילן. ilan. As about it
as about ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah* until ט״ו בשבט Tu
B'Shevat, *Tu B'Shevat*. So here is ט״ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat, *Tu B'Shevat*.
And even though you don't have the next ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah,
*Rosh Hashanah* until here, whatever, so at this stage now is it
considered to be year four because you hit this ט״ו בשבט Tu
B'Shevat, *Tu B'Shevat* in the middle? Okay, so it actually, you would
have thought this was year four, but no, because it becomes a
tree it's not year four until then. And therefore it is not
year five until, although here's the next ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh
Hashanah*, right, it's not year five until it gets into,
right, until it gets into here.
It's a mixing and matching though, right? Like if it's the נטיעה
*netiah* for three years, you could say you need another three years
once it becomes an אילן *ilan*. But no.
Yeah, well, no no. That you don't. ערלה orlah. *orla* is only
three years. Okay, so therefore, so it says that that if it's
for, so the third year stays till ט״ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat, *Tu
B'Shevat*, extends more than a year. It's basically a year and three
kind of a third or whatever. And the fourth year extends to,
to the next, you know, sorry, so this becomes now the fourth,
this third year, right, אסור *assur*, this is אסור *assur* till this
ט״ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat. *Tu B'Shevat* and only here is it totally
מותר *mutar*. Okay, so by the way, I don't know if this
is going to confuse you, but, point you're already confused, but, but
if you actually would not have said any of this, right, if
you would have actually have said that the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah,
*Rosh Hashanah* for whether it's for נטיעה *netiah* or whether for a
tree is ט״ו בשבט Tu B'shvat *Tu B'Shevat*, I think you would
have been better off, right? Because if this wouldn't have been, right,
if basically if we would have just gone by ט״ו בשבט Tu
B'shvat *Tu B'Shevat*, right, if we would have just gone by ט״ו
בשבט Tu B'shvat. *Tu B'Shevat*, so then if it were this scenario
it would be the same, right? This would be year one, then
year two, then year three, and now year four. You'd be fine,
right? It'd be the exact same הלכה halacha *halacha*. It doesn't become
מותר *mutar* until this ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat*. But you'd even be
better off,
because what would be the case if you planted it right here?
If you planted it between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah* and
ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* in this scenario, right, even when you pass
this line you're still in year one. Right? But if you had
ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* for the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah*,
you'd already be in year two. So actually having it like this,
you know, is worse than having it just be ט״ו בשבט *Tu
B'Shevat*. So this is the הלכה *halacha* that you start counting the
years when you hit ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah*, but it
doesn't, but at the back end it needs to actually be a
year and a third. It needs to get to ט״ו בשבט *Tu
B'Shevat* in order to enter into the next year.
Yeah, presumably back in ארץ *Eretz*, if you're planting already sometime like
well into the rainy season, then that's sort of, it's not really
a full year. If you're planting before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh
Hashanah*, then you're definitely getting essentially a full year, a full year,
full rainy season. So presumably that presumably is probably part of the
logic.
Yeah, but the trick is that you get in this full year,
but you get to count this one month as the full year.
That's the trick, right?
No, no, no, so if you planted in טבת *Teves*, right, then
you're not getting a full rainy season. This way it makes sure
that you're going to get that full rainy season.
Right, so you're saying, so you're saying you're right. It does, you,
ah, you're saying you're right, you do have to spend more time
because of having to get to ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* and in
a way that makes a certain sense. You're right. So you could
have said you go by ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* but it has
to be five months before, but we're saying a month before. It's
an interesting way of thinking about it. Okay. So that's what it
says. Okay. And אסור *assur* until ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* אם לערלה
ערלה orlah *im l'orla orla*. The ערלה orlah *orla* applies not till
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*, but the year three goes till
the ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat*, till another third of a year. And
אם לרבעי רבעי revai. *im l'revai revai*, and then the רבעי *revai*
goes to the next ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat*. Okay. מנלן הני מילי
*minalan hani mili*? Where do we know this from? דאמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan. ומטה בה משמיה דרבי
ינאי אמר קרא *de'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan umata
bah mishmei de'Rabbi Yanai amar kra*. So Rabbi Chiya bar Yochanan says
in some sort of leaning, meaning inclined to say that this is
coming from the name of Rabbi Yanai. It's based on the verse:
ובשנה הרביעית ובשנה החמישית *u'bashanah ha'revi'it u'bashanah ha'chamishit*.
It says שלש שנים יהיה לכם ערלים לא יאכל *shalosh shanim yiheye
lachem arelim lo ye'achel*. Three years it is off-limits. ובשנה הרביעית *u'bashanah
ha'revi'it*.
So it's reading שלש שנים *shalosh shanim*, right, שלש שנים יהיה לכם
ערלים *shalosh shanim yiheye lachem arelim*, ערלים
*arelim*, it's off-limits for three years, ובשנה הרביעית *u'bashanah ha'revi'it*. Okay, it
doesn't say בשנה ba-shanah, הרביעית *bashanah ha'revi'it*. It's off-limits for three years
and into the fourth year. Right? You see how it's reading it?
That it says it's off-limits includes the fourth year. So it's not
just off-limits for year three, it's even off-limits into the beginning of
the fourth year, this period of until ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* remains
ערלים *arelim*. And similarly, ובשנה החמישית כל פריו קדש הלולים *u'bashanah ha'chamishit
kol piryo kodesh hilulim*. Right? So the fourth year has a status
of נטע רבעי neta revai. *net-revai*, ובשנה החמישית *u'bashanah ha'chamishit*.
So this status of נטע רבעי *net-revai* applies not only the fourth
year, but and into the fifth year. So the ו׳ *vav* means
the previous status of or applies into the fourth year, and the
previous status of נטע רבעי applies into the fifth year. So here
you're already in the fourth year, right? Because you passed ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah but it's still ערלה. orlah And here you're already into
the fifth year, but you passed... but because you passed ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah but you haven't hit ט״ו בשבט, so it still is
נטע רבעי. ופעמים שברביעית ועדיין אסור משום ערלה, u-peamim she-be-revi'it ve-adayin assur
mishum orlah, sometimes
it's within year four after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah between before ט״ו
בשבט, and still has an ערלה orlah. status. ופעמים שבחמישית ועדיין אסור
משום רבעי, u-peamim she-be-chamishit ve-adayin assur mishum revai,
sometimes it's within the fifth year, it's after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
but it's not yet ט״ו בשבט, and it still is רבעי. Now
again, so but we still we learned from an earlier פסוק pasuk
that תשרי Tishrei is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. for the for the
three years because we learned out גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah בשנה, Beshanah,
whatever, that told us תשרי. Tishrei. This tells us at the back
end, year four and five, for them to be, you know, that
they start later, and we don't know exactly when later, but since
we have this other tradition which we'll get to, that for trees
it goes by ט״ו בשבט, therefore we say that's at the back
end, the beginning ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah at the back end it
goes by ט״ו בשבט.
Yeah, I just figured it out.
What did you just figure out? You had your question? All right.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. לימא דלא כרבי
מאיר. leima de-lo ke-Rabbi Meir. Now let's say this idea of thirty
days. Now we're going to focus on the thirty days at the
front end. What's that idea of being thirty days beforehand before it...
it's a שיטת, shittat, it's a שיטה.
shittah. Yeah, but we're not going to start with שביעית, shevi'it, we'll
get to שביעית shevi'it in a minute. We'll, we're focusing on ערלה
Orlah. now, that it only gets counted as a year if it
started a month before. If it was starting within a month before
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah then it's not enough to increment it and
count it as a year. What's that going on? לימא דלא כרבי
מאיר. leima de-lo ke-Rabbi Meir. Let's say that's not like רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. דאי רבי מאיר הא אמר, de-i Rabbi Meir ha amar,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said יום אחד בשנה חשוב שנה, yom echad
ba-shanah chashuv shanah, even one day would have counted as a year.
We already, like I said, saw that by kings, so he would
say that here too. Okay, now we're not going to quote an
example by ערלה Orlah but something a little more halachic than the
kings, actually something that we'll think is relevant, it's parallel to ערלה.
Orlah, דתניא, de-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, baraita, פר האמור בתורה.
par ha-amur ba-Torah. The Torah
speaks about different types of animals for קרבנות. korbanot. It speaks about
עגל, egel, right? עגל בן בקר לחטאת, egel ben bakar le-chatat, right?
It speaks about an עגל, egel, it speaks about a בן בקר.
ben bakar. Actually those are different. It's just sometimes says עגל. egel.
עגל וכבש בן שנה egel va-keves ben shanah is actually a פסוק,
pasuk, explicitly says an עגל's egel a year old. Then sometimes it
says בן בקר, ben bakar, עגל בן בקר. egel ben bakar. So
the fact that it said בן בקר ben bakar and connected it
with the idea of בקר bakar means an older animal, and the
third is when it actually says פר, par, either פר par or
פר בן בקר. par ben bakar. So those are the three cases,
right? You've got עגל egel by itself, you have עגל בן בקר,
egel ben bakar, which is the phrase that's going to be key,
and then you have פר par whether or not it comes with
בן בקר. ben bakar. Sometimes it says פר בן בקר. par ben
bakar. So עגל egel we're going to say is one year old,
is within its first year, whenever it says בן בקר ben bakar
or עגל בן בקר, egel ben bakar, it's two years old, and
whenever it says פר, par, it's going to be a three-year-old. Okay,
let's take a look. פר האמור בתורה סתם בן עשרים וארבעה חודש
ויום אחד,
par ha-amur
ba-Torah stam ben esrim ve-arba'ah chodesh ve-yom echad, into its third year,
twenty-four months and and one day. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says. Entering into its third year. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer
בן עשרים וארבעה חודש ושלשים יום, ben esrim ve-arba'ah chodesh u-shloshim yom,
no, it has to be thirty days into its
third year. One day is not enough to say
that
it's already a three-year-old. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר, she-hayah Rabbi Meir omer,
because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say, כל מקום שנאמר עגל
בתורה סתם, kol makom she-ne'emar egel ba-Torah stam, whenever it says עגל
egel by itself without בן בקר, ben bakar, בן שנה. ben shanah.
If it says בן בקר, ben bakar, either בן בקר ben bakar
by itself or עגל בן בקר, egel ben bakar, בן שתים, ben
shtayim, two years old. פר, par, if it has פר, par, בן
שלש, ben shalosh, three years. So when is it considered a three-year-old?
Two years and a day. Now again, it's also an interesting question:
are we conceptually saying that it's a three-year-old, or are we saying
that the definition is into its third year? You know, these are
always like questions, right? I mean, for example, תוספות Tosafot says, you
know, when we talk about the age of being בר מצוה bar
mitzvah or בת מצוה bat mitzvah or the age of being,
you know, three years old for a girl in order to be
considered like a reach a certain halachic status, whether it's considered an
act of sex, another type of thing, we say that it's full
years, right? You have to be
thirteen, actually no, I mean what we actually say for בר מצוה,
bar mitzvah, well yeah, we say that you're thirteen. You have to
be
your thirteenth birthday and a day, which means you have thirteen full
years behind you, right? So here, but he quotes an interesting opinion
that says the idea of a three-year-old by a girl for certain
הלכות halachot relating to sex and whatever, we say it's three years
old and a day, but there actually is an opinion that says
two years old and a day. Okay, so it's an interesting question
which is: are we trying to say that the cow is three
years old, but one day makes it like it's three years old,
or are we trying to say the whole definition is into its
third year? The גמרא Gemara presumably understands that the idea here is
that it's saying it's three years old, like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says, פר par is בן שלש שנים, ben shalosh shanim, not in
its third year, a three-year-old. It's defined as a three-year-old. once it
begins its third year, one day in, that makes it like it's
three years. So that says one day. So according to him, the
גמרא Gemara assumes that if it was planted one day before ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah it should be considered to be its second year
for the ערלה. Orlah, Now again, there's a little bit of a
difference, right? Because there it's you're counting from its birthday, twenty-four months
and a day from its birthday. Here you're counting a particular calendar
date; ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah increments it, right? But okay, and those
in the leap were saying that the question is, how old is
the tree? The tree's third year, the cow's third year, it's you
know, how many years old is it? And if the cow is
considered three years old when it's two years and a day, then
the tree also, although it's on a specific day, will be considered
already into its second year once it was just one day preceding.
Yes, of course it's also going to be back end and front
end, which we'll get to in a minute. Yes.
This relates to something we talked about before, but for the for
the trees, for the cows, for the בני מצוה, B'nei Mitzvah, is
it Jewish years or solar years?
Yeah, no, it's always Jewish years. But the question also is, is
it what the גמרא Gemara calls מיום ליום, Miyom Leyom, from the
birthdays, which is what we do for בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah and
cows and so on? And we don't do for trees. Okay? So
trees goes by a calendar date, you know, and it's at the
front end, whereas these other things are going from birthdates and they're
going at the back end. So the גמרא's Gemara going to ask
the difference between front end and back end. Okay, so let's take
a look. But says, at least according to רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir,
logically maybe, planting one day before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah should be
enough; you wouldn't need thirty days. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אפילו תימא רבי מאיר, Afillu teima Rebbe Meir, even according to
רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir. כי קאמר רבי מאיר יום אחד בשנה חשוב
שנה, Ki ka'amar Rebbe Meir yom echad bashanah chashuv shanah, בסוף שנה.
Besof shanah. When did he say one day counts? At the end.
אבל בתחילת שנה לא אמר, Aval bit-chilat shanah lo amar, not at
the beginning. All right, and and you could understand a certain logic
of that, particularly if you want to say you're entering into your
third year. So then you did two full years beforehand and one
extra day began your third year. But to say one day at
the beginning and then passing some arbitrary point like ראש חודש תשרי
Rosh Chodesh Tishrei makes it considered your second year? Maybe it's not
the same. Maybe he only says it at the back end, not
the front. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said, ולא
קל וחומר הוא? Velav kal vachomer hu? It's a קל וחומר. Kal
vachomer.
If it counts at the back end, it should count at the
front. Why? ומה נדה שאין תחילת היום עולה לה בסופה, Umah niddah
she'ein t-chilat hayom oleh lah besofah, סוף היום עולה לה בתחלתה. Sof
hayom oleh lah bit-chilatah. In a נדה, Niddah, the end or the
beginning of a day does not count at the end, and it
counts at the beginning.
What does this mean? It means by a נדה, Niddah, one believes
has her period on a certain day, okay? There it is, let's
look at it like this: Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, and so on
like this, Friday, שבת, Shabbos, Sunday. Okay, let's number these days: three,
four, five, six, seven. Okay, fine. Now this is not how we
practice נדה, Niddah, which is that after a woman stops bleeding, she
needs to count seven clean days, seven days without bleeding. I'll get
to that in a minute. This is the תורה's Torah נדה. Niddah.
The תורה's Torah נדה Niddah says that a woman bleeds, so there's
from the onset there's seven days where she's טמא, Tamei, and at
the end of seven full days she goes to the מקוה Mikvah
the following night. So if a woman bleeds on Sunday at I
don't know, 1 p.m., here she bleeds, this is day one. So
this is the end; שבת Shabbos is the end of the seventh
day, and she goes to the מקוה Mikvah מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos.
Okay, that's the תורה. Torah. Seven days from the onset of bleeding.
You start the onset of bleeding, you count seven days, she goes
to the תורה Torah at the end of the seventh day. So
the גמרא Gemara says, look at this: she bled here at 1
p.m., right? But this still counts as day one of her seven
days. And when she gets here, she can't go to the מקוה
Mikvah at the beginning of day seven; she says the beginning of
the day doesn't count, she needs the full day. Okay, so therefore
in this case, the beginning of the day—let's read that again according
to
רבא—שאין תחילת היום עולה לה בסופה, when שבת Shabbos begins, it doesn't
count like she's she's done with her seven days.
Nevertheless,
סוף היום עולה לה בתחלתה. sof hayom oleh lah bit-chilatah. When she
bleeds here on Sunday, she only has a few hours left of
Sunday, those few hours count as day one. But here the beginning
of day seven doesn't count as day seven; you need all of
day seven. So you see here, it was easier to count the
beginning as a day than it was the end. Okay, so even
a partial thing counts at the beginning, although a partial thing does
not count at the end. At 1 p.m.
on שבת. Shabbos. No, she has to wait till the sun goes.
Yeah, exactly. So if that's true,
אינו דין, Eino din, which is the—I should have applied—בשנה, a year,
where you are saying according to רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir the cows,
I'm sorry, not the cows, the cows, one day counts at the
end. אינו דין, Eino din, is it not—it stands to reason, שיום
אחד עולה בתחילתה, she-yom echad oleh bit-chilatah, that when you're counting
years—so now we're sort of switching from cows to trees, but in
the cow case, if you can count one day at the end,
you should certainly by trees be allowed to count one day at
the beginning. Okay? So basically it's easier to count the beginning of
a process, let's say you began... and now you're into already the
second day than it is at the end. So if by the
cows we allow one day at the end, we should allow it
at the beginning. It gets mighty confusing. So but, one minute, if
you're making a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, then why by cows don't
we count both the beginning and the end? Right? You know, so
at the end and the beginning. We don't count the beginning for
cows. Part of the confusion is, is because by cows it's not
about passing an arbitrary calendar date. By cows the system is, you
know, how many years since your birthday? So the only place you
can do the partial count is at the end. It's been two
full years since your birthday, and now you've begun your third year.
Whereas here, by the trees, we're counting about a calendar date. So
by the trees the only logic it really makes when you hit
the date is when you increment, so the only question here is
a partial thing at the beginning. You understand the logic? The only
opportunity here to count a partial is a partial before the calendar
date. Whereas by a cow the only opportunity to count a partial
is a partial, you know, after a certain number of years from
the birthday you've begun the next year. But basing on נידה niddah
that says if in some circumstances we see that it's easier when
you're beginning a process to say, oh, okay, you began it here
already, here you're at day two. As opposed to at the end
we don't say you began day seven and you're done. Okay, so
the trees here it's easier to begin a process. So here too,
if by the cow case you can count the end as already
the year, here the fact that you began and then you began
in here, it's easier to say, well, now you're already into year
two. That's the קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Is it from a נידה niddah to a tree or
from a נידה niddah to a cow?
From a נידה niddah using the example of נידה niddah to set
up what's easier to say, and then use that model to say
and therefore if you can do something by a cow at the
end, you should certainly be able to do it by a tree
at the beginning. All right, so just go with it, all right?
Obviously a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but okay.
I'm sure you thought that
נידה, niddah, trees, and cows
was exactly the
perfect for a parody.
By the way, not to confuse you anymore,
but רש"י Rashi makes the point that he says some people make
a major mistake based on this גמרא Gemara and they say that
they confuse it with the way we keep הלכות נידה. hilchos niddah.
So the way we keep הלכות נידה hilchos niddah is that, you
know, to keep on going this Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, is that
a woman let's say gets her period here, we need seven clean
days. So normally at least the way אשכנזים Ashkenazim do it,
let's say we wait, you know, she bleeds for a few, let's
forget the way exactly אשכנזים Ashkenazim do it nowadays. But at least
she bleeds for a few days, and then she counts her seven
clean days, right? And then it would be one, two, three, four
where she wouldn't bleed, five, six, seven, and then she goes to
the מקוה. mikvah. Okay. רש"י Rashi says some people make a mistake
and say, oh, it says by נידה niddah you can count the
beginning. So that means if on Wednesday she stops bleeding at 2:00
PM on Wednesday, if it says by נידה niddah you count the
beginning, right? That's what it says, you count the beginning by נידה.
niddah. You can count already the remainder of Wednesday as day one,
right? Some people make that mistake in their mind, but that's completely
wrong. That's what the גמרא Gemara says that the Samaritans used to
do, totally not true. We're not talking about the clean days. We're
talking about and we're not talking about the rabbinic way of viewing
נידה, niddah, we're talking about the way it is biblically. Okay, so,
and because actually the rabbinic way would be quite the opposite, and
so there's a whole question, well, if it's the opposite there, what
does that mean? The beginning is easier than the end? Anyway, to
confuse you a little bit more, let's get back to the גמרא.
Gemara.
What do אשכנזים Ashkenazim do there? Do they count a full day
or not?
You need to be, it's only the day after the bleeding stops
which counts as a clean day. Okay?
That's your first full day. It has to be an end, right?
As as an end, right. But that's because תוספות Tosafos basically says
the reason there you can't count a partial day as beginning is
because you can't call it a blood-free day because part of the
day was bleeding. So he says that's a very different type of
a reality. Here, the day when we count seven days from the
onset of bleeding, you don't have to say that it was a
blood-free day, it's actually the bleeding day. So partial bleeding on the
day counts as well. So it becomes fun when trying to count
it as a blood-free day, then you can't count a partial day
because part of the day there was bleeding. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Fine. Anyway, what we're saying is that if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says by the cows one day at the end counts, then רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir should say by the trees as well you shouldn't
need 30 days, even one day before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah? it
should be considered to be the second year when ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah, comes around. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, אלא מאי, ela mai, so what do you want to say?
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you want to say it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by the cows said 30 days,
right? So again, we're assuming the cows you can apply it to
the trees. So that's what you want to say. This is רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that means 30 days. If that's not true, according
to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, שלושים ושלושים, shloshim u-shloshim, you need two
thirties, you need 60 days. What is this? דתנן, de-tnan, says you're
forgetting something. All you're looking at is how much time before ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah. but by trees there's another issue. It only starts
to matter once it takes root. You can only start counting the
time that it's been planted. planted not when it goes in the
ground, but after it's actually struck root, and then is it considered
to be really planted? And that takes time. So let's take a
look.
How do you know?
אין נוטעים ואין מבריכים ואין מרכיבים,
ein note'in
ve'ein mavrichin ve'ein markivin, same thing is you can't do plant and
bend over and
graft, ערב שביעית פחות מל' יום לפני ראש השנה, erev shevi'it pachos
mi-l' yom lifnei Rosh Hashanah, you can't do it within thirty days
before
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, ואם נטע והבריך והרכיב, ve-im nata ve-hivrich ve-hirkiv,
and if you did any of these things within thirty days, יעקור,
ya'akor, you'll have to uproot it. That's, okay, they take out the
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. That's thirty days.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, כל
הרכבה שאינה קולטת בג' ימים שוב אינה קולטת. kol harkava she-eina koletet
b-g' yamim shuv eina koletet. No, three days. It's not thirty days,
it's only, once, if he says grafting, but presumably the גמרא Gemara
assumes this applies to everything, that it only takes three days to
take root. And therefore, if you planted it more than three days
before, you're in the clear. You don't need thirty days before. רבי
יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rabbi Yossi ve-Rabbi Shimon omrim, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say, שתי שבתות. shteishabbatos. No, two
weeks it takes to take root. So if you planted it more
than two weeks before you're in the clear, within two weeks you're
not in the clear. Now, this basically is saying that by שמיטה,
shmita, I'm going to read this like תוספות, Tosafos, because רש"י's Rashi
way will get a little confused. The תוספות Tosafos basically says we're
now rejecting the assumption that we had before, which was that the
idea of thirty days before שמיטה shmita is significant because you can't
plant it during the תוספת tosefet period.
The reason of what you can't do before שמיטה shmita is not
you can't plant during the תוספת tosefet period. You can't plant something
before שמיטה shmita in a way that it will take root on
שמיטה. shmita. And therefore, how long do you need for something to
take root? So here is the debate. The first opinion says you
need thirty days. So if you planted it within thirty days of
שמיטה, shmita, then it will have taken root on שמיטה, shmita, and
then you have to uproot it. The other one says, no, it
only takes three days. So as long as you planted it four
days before שמיטה, shmita, it took root before שמיטה, shmita, you're safe.
And two weeks. So all of these, forget תוספת. tosefet. All of
these are just about how long it takes to take root, and
you can't plant it before שמיטה shmita in a way that it
will take root on שמיטה, shmita, and if you did, it gets
uprooted. Okay, but there we see a concept that it takes a
certain amount of time to take root, and we're going to assume
that the same way that's true in terms of the problem of
having something take root on שמיטה, shmita, for this thing to be
considered to get to year two by a new planting, it wouldn't
start counting its time until it actually took root. So now here's
the גמרא's Gemara question. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, ve-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar
Avuha, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman says in the name of רבה
בר אבוה, Rabbah bar Avuha, לדברי האומר ל', le-divrei ha-omer l', according
to the one that says it takes thirty days to take root,
so when it comes to ערלה Orlah. laws, צריך ל' ושלשים, tzarich
l' u-shloshim, then if you want it to be year two for
ערלה, Orlah you need thirty and thirty. You need thirty days for
it to take root and then the next thirty days for it
to count as the first year. לדברי האומר ג', le-divrei ha-omer g',
the one that says it takes three days to take root, we'll
get to that, but no, because the assumption is it doesn't count
as a tree yet until it's planted, until it's taken root. It's
like רש"י Rashi says, just like it's in your home, it's like
it's still wrapped up in the wrapping. לדברי האומר ב' שבתות, le-divrei
ha-omer b' shabbatos, according to the one that says two weeks to
take root, so if you want it to count as a year
for ערלה, Orlah צריך ב' שבתות ושלשים. tzarich b' shabbatos u-shloshim. First
it needs to take root, then you need the thirty days, the
thirty days.
The thirty days is the תוספת. tosefet.
Not תוספת, tosefet, we're not talking about שמיטה shmita now, we're talking
about ערלה. Orlah It's the thirty days for thirty days of the
year count as a year. Okay, where were we? לדברי
האומר ב' שבתות צריך ב' שבתות ושלשים יום. le-divrei ha-omer b' shabbatos
tzarich b' shabbatos u-shloshim yom. So again, by שמיטה shmita we're throwing
out the idea of תוספת. tosefet. By שמיטה shmita the idea is
about taking root on שמיטה. shmita. But now that we see it
takes time to take root, so if by ערלה Orlah. you need,
A, for it first to take root, and then you need the
requisite thirty days. So you got a problem anyway. How come the
ברייתא Baraisa before said ערלה Orlah. said thirty days? Thirty days shouldn't
be enough based on how long it takes to take root. You'd
need thirty-three days or forty-four days or
sixty days. The גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, the גמרא Gemara
says
like
this, ואינמי כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה ג' ושלשים בעי. ve-inami ke-Rabbi Yehuda
sevira leh g' u-shloshim ba'ei. So even if we held like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says three days, the smallest amount of time
you would need for ערלה Orlah is thirty-three days. So how does
our משנה Mishnah say thirty days? The גמרא Gemara goes back, אלא
לעולם רבי מאיר. ela le-olam Rabbi Meir. You're right. The גמרא Gemara
says, I'm going to reverse it on you. We thought רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that by the cows said one day was the problem
because we said you need thirty days for ערלה. Orlah, Now רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir going to help us, because the ברייתא Baraisa said
you needed thirty days for ערלה. Orlah. Now we said, okay, but
thirty days for ערלה Orlah isn't enough because you need the amount
of time to take root plus the amount of time to count
as a year. So now we actually have a way which רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir who says one day is the amount of time
for to count as a year to work out. It's thirty days
that it says you need it for ערלה, Orlah it's the thirty
days to take root, because that's what also the ברייתא Baraisa also
said you need. That ברייתא Braita that said 30 days, remember we
started with the ברייתא Braita that says if you planted 30 days
before, then come שמיטה, Shmita, within 30 days you have to uproot
it, it doesn't count as a year. So that ברייתא Braita is
assuming that it needs 30 days to take root because that's the
amount of time that's relevant for שמיטה, Shmita, 30 days before שמיטה
Shmita you have to uproot it. Ah, that's also why 30 days
counts for ערלה. Orlah, So he holds דווקא davka like רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that one day is enough. So you have the 30
days to take root plus one day. And therefore you've got it
took root and you got your one day and now you can
already start the new year. 30 plus 1, 31. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אלא לעולם, Ella l'olam, where was it? רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וכי קאמר ל' לקליטה. Vechi ka'amar lamed liklita.
The whole reason the ברייתא Braita there said 30 days before ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah, for שמיטה Shmita and ערלה Orlah is the 30
days to take root. But this is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir of
the cows that says for ערלה Orlah, purposes one day counts. So
the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי ל"א בעי? Iy hachi lamed aleph
ba'ee? You should need 31?
No, קסבר יום ל' עולה לכאן ולכאן. kasavar yom lamed oleh lekan
ulekan.
It's like the ברייתא Braita said double duty, except not double duty
the whole time, double duty the last day.
Okay, so you basically went ahead and you planted this tree right
right
here on the last day of of what comes before אלול? Elul?
אב. Av. Okay, you planted it on the last day of אב.
Av. So Rosh- so this is day one and then you get
to the 29th of אלול, Elul, that's day 30. So because day
30 began, because you entered into day 30, that's considered now it
took root on day 30. Not the end of day 30, but
the middle of day 30. And then you have a few hours
left and that even partial day counts now as your one day
like the one day by the cow at the back end. So
you have a partial day within this day 30. The first part
of it it ended taking root and the second part it began
and that's your partial day and then the year begins and you're
in year two. Okay, so that's how it solves it. But it
actually points out that the ברייתא Braita says 30 days before ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah for שמיטה Shmita and for
planting. It's flipping it up until now it thought the 30 days
was to mean you need the month to count as the year.
Now it's saying no, no, no, the 30 days is you need
30 days to take root and that's why it's relevant for שמיטה
Shmita to take root before שמיטה Shmita or during שמיטה. Shmita. And
therefore by ערלה, orlah it's really just assuming you really just need
one day and you can use the last day to do double
duty. And that's why it works for ערלה as well. But the
30 days is time it takes to take root. And really one
day counts as a day. So the גמרא Gemara says as a
whole year. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan Now רבי יוחנן says.
בשתיהם מקרא אחד דרשו. Bishteihem mikra echad darshu. They both interpreted the
same verse.
This idea whether you need one day to count as a year
or a month to count as a year. Okay, now whatever, I
don't get what we're about to read, but let's go for it.
ויהי באחת ושש מאות שנה בראשון באחד לחדש. Vayehi b'achat ushesh me'ot
shanah barishon b'echad lachodesh. On the 601st year, this is in the
story of the מבול, mabul, on the first month on the first
of the day,
you know, the מבול mabul sort of began to abate. חרבו המים.
Cherevu hamayim.
What? נסכרו כל מעינות תהום. Niskru kol mayinot tehom. No, this is
towards- this is
when it ends, not when it begins, right?
ויבשה הארץ. Veyavesha ha'aretz. Right. חרבו המים מעל- Cherevu hamayim me'al what
is it? מעל הארץ. me'al ha'aretz. חרבו המים מעל הארץ. Cherevu hamayim
me'al ha'aretz. Okay, so it began to dry up, fine. Okay. רבי
מאיר סבר Rabbi Meir savar מדכתיב midgektiv יום אחד הוא, yom echad
hu, it's just one day, first day, first month of the next
year. It's one day דהוה בשנה וקרי ליה שנה. dehava bashana vekarei
lei shana. And it says it's the 601st year. So you see,
שמע מינה יום אחד בשנה חשוב שנה. shema mina yom echad bashana
chashiv shana. One day in a year counts as a year. Like
I don't begin to understand this. It's the
601st year, not 601 years have
completed. It's the beginning of the 601st year. But somehow he says
because it says באחת ושנה b'achat veshana like it's- it counts as
if the whole year's already
passed. Or if it says it's the third year, not three years.
Right here you by the cows it say- if you say that
you need the third year then fine, it's not a big חידוש.
chiddush. But the גמרא’s Gemara framing it as if the idea is
you need three years and it's as if it's a full three
years. But this is the 601st year. But somehow he's reading the
verse as if it says after 601 years have already passed as
in the 601st year. Okay, anyway,
שמע מינה יום אחד בשנה חשוב שנה. shema mina yom echad bashana
chashiv shana. You see one day is a year. ואידך, Ve'idach, the
other one says no. אי כתיב בשש מאות ואחת שנה, Iee ketiv
beshesh me'ot ve'achat shana,
601 years and maybe and the word אחת achat would be near
שנה, shana, הכי קאמרת hachi ka'amrit then you'd be right, then it's
one day and we're already calling it like it's 601 years that
passed. השתא דכתיב באחת ושש מאות שנה, Hashata deketiv b'achat ushesh me'ot
shana, since it says אחת achat before the שנה, shana, שנה שש
מאות קאי, shana shesh me'ot kai, it's only
600 full years. מאי אחת? Mai achat? אתחלתא דאחת. At'chalta d'achat. We
began the next year. So again, I understand the response saying it
doesn't mean 601 years it means 601st year. I don't exactly get
why it matters where the word אחת achat would have appeared. But
the answer seems to be it means. 600 and 601st year, not
600 and 1 year. Okay, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says you need a month. מאי טעמא דכתיב? mai ta'ama de-chtiv?
What's his reasoning that you need a full month into a year
to count as a year? דכתיב, de-chtiv, the verse says בראשון באחד
לחודש, barishon beachad lachodesh, because the same פסוק pasuk by נח
Noach says on the first day in the first of the month.
מדקאמר יום אחד הוא דאייא בחודש, mide-ka'amar yom echad hu de-aya bachodesh,
it's only one day into the month, וקא קרי ליה חודש, veka
kara lei chodesh, and it already calls it a month. But again,
same playful weird logic. Okay, it's the first month but his reading
is not saying it's the first month, he's reading it to say
it's been already one month. It's already one month old, the year,
which is, you know, not what the פסוק pasuk is saying. Anyway,
it's only one day old and it's already calling it one month
old.
One day into
the month and it's already calling it one month old. Again, it's
not calling it a month old, it's saying it's in the first
month. Nevertheless, שמע מינה יום אחד בחודש חשוב חודש. shma mina yom
echad bachodesh chashuv chodesh. You see one day counts as a whole
month. Now what does that tell you about a year? How you
make an analogy, it's like in, what do they call those on
your SATs, A is to B as C is to D?
Analogy. See, I didn't even know that SAT word. But okay, but
anyway, so מדיום אחד בחודש חשוב חודש, mide-yom echad bachodesh chashuv chodesh,
if one day, one day is to a year, as X, one
day is to a month as X is to a year. So
what's the X? One day is to a month as a month
is to a year. So מדיום אחד בחודש חשוב חודש, mide-yom echad
bachodesh chashuv chodesh, שמע מינה יום השנה חשובים שנה. shma mide-yom hashana
chashuvim shana.
30 days in a year count as a year. חודש מנוייו שנה
מנוייו. chodesh minuyav shana minuyav. You
do a month
you go by one of its units, a month is made up
of days, so one unit counts as if it's the whole month
already, and a year was made up of months. Now why don't
we do 29? I don't know, because 30 is, you know, you
always have at 30 is always a month and therefore a month
counts as a year.
Yeah, there's another question is, we don't say, I don't think we
say a day is מעת לעת, me'eis l'eis, we say it's from
morning till night. Right. So why do we say a month is
from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh until the end of the month?
Yeah, yeah, it's true.
Well, I guess, you're right, so when we say יום אחד בחודש
חשוב חודש, yom echad bachodesh chashuv chodesh, presumably it would be even
if there was only two hours left of it. So why don't
we say here right, whatever much time is, is that what you're
saying, how much time is left of the month?
No, I'm saying when you say יום אחד בחודש חשוב חודש, yom
echad bachodesh chashuv chodesh, you mean Monday, not Monday 2 p.m. till
Tuesday 2 p.m.
Oh, no, well I'm not even aware what are the times we
say יום אחד בחודש חשוב חודש, yom echad bachodesh chashuv chodesh, other
than the day. Right, the
day, meaning you don't say till Tuesday 2 p.m., you say till
the end of the day.
30 days is not the same as a month.
Right, but if you said a month, you would say from
ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul to ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh
Tishrei or whatever.
Right, you would need a full unit. Right, yeah, it's true.
Then what, we make our מצווה mitzvah when someone's like 12 and
a half years?
Don't ask me what any of that means. All right, we're moving
on. But the upshot is, for שמיטה, Shmita, the way the גמרא
Gemara is concluding, רש"י Rashi reads it slightly differently but I'm going
to tell you תוספות's Tosafot way which is easier, you need, the
issue is not תוספת. tosefet. Whatever your תוספת tosefet is doesn't matter.
The idea that you have to uproot it is if it took
root on שמיטה. Shmita. So the only question is, did you plant
it with enough time so it took root before שמיטה Shmita regardless
of the תוספת tosefet discussion, that's how תוספות Tosafot reads the conclusion,
תוספת tosefet is not the issue. By ערלה, you first need it
to take root, and that's a week, that's two weeks, three days,
or a month, and then what you needed to do is you
need actually, what do you call, then you need an amount of
time that counts like you, like it's been enough time so that
by the time it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. it's already considered to
entered in the second year. And that could be a day between
a day or a month. So after it's taken root, you need
either a day or a month so that by the time of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. now it already can be considered to enter
in the second year. I should say that this idea of it
taking the three days or two weeks or a month to take
root raises interesting questions in הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos because one of,
you know, the מלאכות melachos on שבת Shabbos is like planting a
seed or planting a tree or whatever. So the question is, if
you plant it on שבת Shabbos but it hasn't done anything until
it takes root after, so the question is what happens if after
שבת Shabbos is over you go back and you pull the tree
out of the ground? Have you been מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos retrospectively,
have you been מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos or not?
Maybe planting has a different definition for מלאכה melacha and for for
the tree.
Right,
it could be, so it could be that the מלאכה melacha is
defined as putting it in the scenario where things continue naturally, it
will take root even if in the end it doesn't take root,
right? So what about, because the גמרא Gemara has a case about
cooking that the גמרא Gemara says that if you put something on
the fire and you take it off before it's cooked, you actually
have not retrospectively you have not violated שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so there
by cooking it actually does have to achieve the state of being
cooked. But then the question becomes well but what if you put
on the fire and it finished cooking after שבת? Shabbos? Right? Do
you violate then? Is it that the act is the initial act
on the condition that it complete? Anyway, so this idea of things
that take time to complete becomes interesting in a שבת Shabbos context
which is not ours, but the idea that you could not have,
you know, that the planting you did is not significant until two
weeks or a month later can be very interesting. Yeah.
This discussion sounds
like...
Supposing that the timing it takes to take root before שמיטה Shemita
is running concurrently with the thirty days you need from going to
the mundane to the
holy?
No, that's what I'm saying. I'm saying this is ignoring the תוספת.
Tosefet. There's a separate issue of תוספת Tosefet which is not about
planting things, like I can't plow the land within the month before,
the תוספת Tosefet is a month, and some things I can't even
do from פסח Pesach or from שבועות Shavuot before. So there's a
period of תוספת Tosefet which is, which is different. Obviously, תוספת Tosefet
would apply here as well, but here for the הלכה that we'd
have to be uprooted is irrespective of the issue of תוספת. Tosefet.
The uprooting, the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, is a function of
the, only a function of whether it took root on שמיטה Shemita
or not. Okay?
But would you need sixty days then really?
Well, you might need sixty days to allow you to do it,
meaning to, there's one question about uprooting, and to allow you to
do it you might also have to be outside of the תוספת
Tosefet period. So let's take the position that says three days. Are
you allowed to plant this four days before שמיטה? Shemita? You know,
maybe the answer is no, maybe you're right, maybe because of תוספת
Tosefet you have to wait, you can only plant it a month
before. But you went ahead and you violated תוספת Tosefet and you
planted it four days before. According to one opinion, you're still allowed
to keep it, you don't have to uproot it because at least
in the end of the day it took root before שמיטה Shemita
began. So that's exactly correct. That's רש״י Rashi reads that you need
both, but תוספות Tosafot reads that they're independent, okay? There's a תוספת
Tosefet question which is did you plant it where you were allowed
to, and then there's the uprooting question which is did it take
root on שמיטה Shemita or before שמיטה? Shemita? Yes.
You're tacking on extra period from ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. to ט״ו
בשבט for release and the ערלה purposes? Yeah.
Does that hold, how early, when does that kick in? What if
we planted it in July? It's way more than thirty days.
Yeah, you mean if you planted it way back here on like
even before ט״ו בשבט or something like that, you know, would you
have to, could you here go by ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah You
know, so there is some opinion out there that the only reason
you have to do extra time here is because you sort of
got off easy over here, but that's not generally the position, the
assumption. The general consensus is no matter how many, how long it
was before ראש השנה, at the back end it's always going to
go to ט״ו בשבט.
And the reason for that
is because then it's considered a tree and not a sapling. Okay,
so let's just read a little bit more, finish the דף. daf.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, on the ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי אליעזר אומר בתשרי
נברא העולם. Rabbi Eliezer omer bitishrei nivra haolam. Okay,
now that we're talking about the verses from
נח, Noach, it says whether it was the first day of the
first month, we want to figure out what month are we talking
about. When was the world created and therefore also the question about
the early counting in the Torah, before החודש הזה לכם ראש חדשים,
hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim,
before ניסן Nissan is established in the story of מצרים Mitzrayim as
the first month. What was the initial counting in the Torah? At
the place where we have, the only place where we have dates
in the Torah of the months of the year and the year,
is by the נח Noach story. So is that counting from תשרי
Tishrei or is that counting from ניסן? Nissan? We're going to be
looking at those פסוקים psukim a lot tomorrow. But we're going to
start with these two statements: רבי אליעזר אומר בתשרי נברא העולם, Rabbi
Eliezer omer bitishrei nivra haolam, the world was created in תשרי, Tishrei,
בתשרי נולדו אבות, bitishrei noldu avos, the forefathers were born except for
יצחק, Yitzchak, as we'll see in אברהם Avraham and
יעקב, Yaakov, בתשרי מתו אבות, bitishrei metu avos, they died in תשרי,
Tishrei, an assumption that they lived out full years, so they died
in the month that they were born in.
They did or more?
Right. בפסח נולד יצחק, Be-Pesach nolad Yitzchak, the one exception is
by יצחק, Yitzchak, בפסח נולד יצחק. Be-Pesach nolad Yitzchak. Why is he
an exception? Because of the next line: בראש השנה נפקדה שרה רחל
וחנה. Be-Rosh Hashanah nifkeda Sarah Rachel veChannah. When it says וה׳ פקד
את שרה, v'Hashem pakad et Sarah, right? Or by חנה, Channah, right?
We, there's a reason we read those on ראש השנה. It's a
day of remembrance, so שרה Sarah was remembered, which means that she
became pregnant. So she became pregnant on ראש השנה, then she gave
birth on פסח. Pesach. Of course that's a premature pregnancy, it's only
six months. All right, so we'll see. But the idea that יצחק
Yitzchak was the one that was born on פסח Pesach is a
function of saying that שרה, Sarah, together with רחל Rachel and חנה,
Channah, were remembered on ראש השנה, which means they became pregnant. Okay.
בראש השנה יצא יוסף מבית האסורים, Be-Rosh Hashanah yatza Yosef mibeit haasurim,
יוסף Yosef was remembered, again it's a day of remembrance, so Pharaoh
remembered him and he came, he was freed from jail. בראש השנה
בטלה עבודה מאבותינו במצרים, Be-Rosh Hashanah batla avoda meavoteinu beMitzrayim, they were
freed from being enslaved in Egypt, meaning imagine that even before the
actual redemption and the פסח Pesach events of פסח, Pesach, they, Pharaoh,
already the Egyptians were having enough and they sort of at least,
you know, remember before we had the whole idea of the slaves
not being enslaved but not being free from ראש השנה to יום
כיפור? Yom Kippur? So we're seeing now a parallel of that idea
in Mi- Maybe that's where it came from, one may have informed
the other. So that already stopped on ראש השנה. בניסן נגאלו, B'Nissan
nigalu, and in ניסן Nissan they were redeemed, בתשרי עתידין להגאל, B'Tishrei
asidin lehiga'el, but the future redemption would be in תשרי. Tishrei. So
this position basically gives everything to תשרי Tishrei except the few things
you have to give to ניסן. Nissan. The only two things you
have to give to ניסן Nissan are יצחק, Yitzchak, because שרה Sarah
was remembered in תשרי, Tishrei, that forces ניסן Nissan to יצחק Yitzchak
to be in ניסן, Nissan, and פסח. Pesach. But other than יצחק
Yitzchak and פסח, Pesach, everything was תשרי. Tishrei. Okay, that's one approach.
That's רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. But if בניסן נגאלו, B'Nissan nigalu, בתשרי, B'Tishrei, why would
we... I mean נגאלו בניסן?
nigalu B'Nissan? Okay, but you have the פסוקים. pesukim. Now why was
ניסן Nissan given importance for the original גאולה geulah and not the
others? We'll get to that, but at least understand conceptually, everything is
תשרי Tishrei except the two things that were in ניסן Nissan had
to be in ניסן. Nissan.
I'm not holding on to why this is brought here because of
רבי אליעזר... Rabbi Eliezer...
No, because we were quoting the פסוקים pesukim of, well, some understand
that the גמרא, Gemara, it's had the words in parentheses we skip
and understand that the debate before about thirty days or one day
and whatever somehow indicated whether you were reading the verses talking about
ניסן Nissan or תשרי. Tishrei. It's hard to see the link, so
we took out those words. But the simple reason is because a
lot of it is going to have to do with unpacking the
פסוקים pesukim from נח. Noach. Since we've been using those פסוקים pesukim
from נח Noach of the six hundred and first year, first day,
first month, etc., we're going to go back to unpack those פסוקים
pesukim to try to play out this debate in that context. So
let's just read the two opinions. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says everything
was תשרי Tishrei except the two things that had to be ניסן,
Nissan,
and רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, and he gives primacy to
ניסן. Nissan. בניסן נברא העולם. B'Nissan nivra ha'olam. בניסן נולדו אבות. B'Nissan
noldu avos. They were remembered in ניסן... Nissan... the world was created
in ניסן, Nissan, the forefathers were born in ניסן. Nissan. בניסן מתו
אבות, B'Nissan mesu avos, they died in ניסן. Nissan. בפסח נולד יצחק.
B'Pesach nolad Yitzchak. Not only were they remembered, not only were אברהם
Avraham and יעקב Yaakov born in ניסן, Nissan, even פסח, Pesach, even
יצחק, Yitzchak, he was born on פסח. Pesach. Now, because יצחק Yitzchak
was born on פסח, Pesach, that leads to one thing had to
be on ראש השנה. בראש השנה נפקדה שרה רחל וחנה. B'Rosh Hashanah
nifkeda Sarah Rachel v'Channah. Okay, so somehow because we agree that יצחק
Yitzchak was born on פסח, Pesach, we're all going to agree that
שרה, Sarah, רחל, Rachel, and חנה Channah happened on ראש השנה. בראש
השנה יצא יוסף מבית האסורים. B'Rosh Hashanah yatza Yosef mi'beis ha'asurim. יוסף
Yosef was taken out of the jail. בראש השנה בטלה עבודה מאבותינו
במצרים. B'Rosh Hashanah batla avoda me'avoseinu b'Mitzrayim.
They were freed from their slavery in מצרים, Mitzrayim, or whatever they
stopped having to work. בניסן נגאלו ובניסן עתידין להגאל. B'Nissan nigalu u'v'Nissan
asidin lehiga'el. So they were freed in ניסן, Nissan, they will be
redeemed in ניסן. Nissan. So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is a slightly
more complicated one. The way to remember at least primarily the two
things are יוסף מבית האסורים Yosef mi'beis ha'asurim and שרה רחל וחנה
Sarah Rachel v'Channah are all the idea of פקד. pakad. So the
idea that like ראש השנה is a time when השם Hashem remembers
and השם פקד, Hashem pakad, right? That everybody agrees to. Okay, and
therefore those two things he does agree to. Why also the forefathers
were freed,
or stopped having to be enslaved, that's also not so clear. So
the first one is easier to understand, that it's basically all about
תשרי. Tishrei. This obviously is fundamentally about ניסן, Nissan, but there are
certain things that he sort of concedes were on תשרי Tishrei and
we will play this all out tomorrow.